Clearly, the position of the chairman and the
MD should be separate, and this separation is
not just on paper, but should be actual.
In situations where you have a chairman who
is also perhaps signing checks or approving matters
reserved for management, it does not speak well
of this expected separation.
Availability for board responsibilities is also a major
feature of the composition and structure of the
board.
So whilst boards sometimes look out for heavyweights,
for want of a better expression, to appoint
to the board, one principal criteria should be
how available are these directors to properly discharge
their duties and responsibilities to the board.
And so there is a concern around being
overboarded.
So you have directors appointing multiple board seats,
accepting to sit on multiple boards at the
same time.
So boards are reminded to manage the number
of directors, the number of other boards that
their directors sit on.
So for instance, the CAMA 2020 has restricted
the number of public companies that a director
can sit on to five.
So you can't be a director of more
than five public company boards at the same
time.
The restriction does not apply to private company
boards.
However, each board is expected to define how
many other boards a director on their board
should sit on, essentially just to help ensure
that the directors are available and committed to
the board on which he or she is
sitting.
So another aspect of the structure of the
board is that the board should have an
effective committee system.
And the code recommends that there should be
at least an audit committee, a governance and
remuneration committee, risk management committee.
And this committee should also have charters or
terms of reference that define their mandates, composition,
tenure and frequency of review of those charters.
Another element of board effectiveness is the effective
use of board committees.
Board committees typically are responsible for drilling down
on specific issues, forming an opinion on such
issues and making recommendations to the board.
And to be effective, the committees themselves should
have committee charters that set out the purpose,
the composition, the authority and the tenure of
committee members.
They should have effective chairs.
So the board should, in fact, the board
typically or the chairman in some cases, the
one that appoints committee chairs, and such chairs
should be available to have the strength of
character and should have the relevant skills to
gain the confidence of their peers.
Committees are accountable to the board.
So while committees can deliberate on issues, all
they can do at the end of the
day is to make recommendations to the board.
Committees are not expected to bind the board
or the company with regards to decisions that
they take.
They should have access to information and they
should have access to training and development.
Another key element of board effectiveness is, of
course, board dynamics.
This is how directors interact with one another
and how they essentially behave as directors.
Individuals come to the board with their egos
and their own self-awareness or lack thereof.
All of this can impact how the board
or directors interact or take decisions.
So the language, emotional intelligence, all of this
go towards constructive debates or otherwise on the
board.
And so it impacts also the quality of
board decisions.
So what are some of the individual attributes
of a director that can promote board dynamics?
Such a director will work well with others,
can disagree but should not be disagreeable, will
possess the required business or industry knowledge, prepares
for and attends meetings punctually and regularly.
There's nothing as instructive to a board as
a director who attends meetings without preparing, reading
through their board papers or doing the required
research ahead of board meetings.
Directors should contribute quality conversations to the board
and to the affairs of the business.